Man, I knew that this was the final stage of evolution.
You just end up sitting in a chair, wires hooked into your brain, and play video games.
God, I hope this is our future.
I want to be one of these dudes sitting in these chairs, playing video games, all day.
Oh yeah, with my brain, of course.
We unlocked some new glyphs, so I want to go back and see if I can understand what people were saying.
And potentially, maybe, decipher new stuff.
This thing... What was the deal with this thing?
Oh yeah, right.
Do I know any of these now, actually?
Talk, key... Ah!
This could be considered a key... No, that's a key, of course.
Door, dead, seek, may create... No, I don't have unlock... yet.
Oh, door!
Door, door, door.
I know that one.
Okay, so if this is a key symbol, perhaps the unlock symbol is similar to this symbol, here.
What looks like it?
Seek.
Could it be any of these other ones?
It's not help.
Seek?
No.
No, it's got to be unlock, right?
It's the only way.
I'm also curious how I'm going to get the molds to forge the other keys I need for the secret doors and all the other levels.
Let's sit over here.
Okay, so what are you saying?
Do I understand it now?
Me, something.
Me, something, tower.
Huh.
Some kind of verb.
I love the tower.
I don't know.
This looks similar to some of the other glyphs we have.
No, actually, I was thinking of that one, which is that.
Do I have anything here that makes sense with what I have there?
Oh, man, I don't know what this could be.
This could be me.
Because I don't really fit into any of the civilizations.
Kind of lonely, isolated, you know?
Talk.
Hmm.
It could be just humans.
You know?
Ah, but wait a minute.
These are already revealed.
So, there's no point putting these in.
It has to be some of these.
Yeah.
Okay, I don't understand what you're saying.
I gotta go back to the stuff over here and speak to you.
See what you're saying.
Perhaps what this person is saying is related to what's happening on the monitor.
Go away.
I hate you, maybe?
What the hell is happening here?
Is that what you're saying?
Hate?
Why else would you say go away?
I despise you.
I warn you, go away from me.
Could be a thing.
You just want to be left alone.
You want to play your video game.
You want to live in this alternate reality.
In virtual worlds.
The real world is not good enough for you.
I get that.
Power.
You know, this could also mean no access.
Like, it's a cross.
Don't go in there, you know?
Access restricted.
Let's just write that as well.
Uh...
No, no access or, uh...
Not?
No?
No access.
Hmm.
It's kind of funny that...
So this is definitely the final level, right?
We can agree on that.
And the way to unlock these glyphs is to sort of combine the meanings of all the other languages in these rotating terminals.
It brings everything together in a way.
Like, look at this.
Not only do we have stuff from the bards, we also have stuff from the devotees, you know, and the warriors.
Everything.
It's kind of cool.
I like it.
Alright, let's just move on.
Down this way where we just were.
Because there was more to be seen.
Wait.
Did I come from here?
See, I'm already lost.
I'm so bad with directions.
Oh, right.
So I went that way before, I think.
Let's go up here.
These stairs look really cool.
Oh my god!
What the hell is this?
Things come out of the eyes and go into the mouth.
Looks like a data stream.
Information packets.
Beautiful background.
Whoa!
Oh, that was cool.
God is on up high.
But they only consider these people gods because of their advanced technology.
In fact, something I've noticed, every single time we advance one level, technology gets better.
Think about that.
The warriors, you know, they have advanced swords and combat routines and all that on the next level.
They have these boats with the rotating motors or whatever.
And the level above that, you know, it gets even crazier.
Okay.
Man, human.
I know that already though.
Alright.
Time to rotate.
Okay, let's see.
So the inner one, I cannot rotate, so this needs to be a knot.
Oh, I think I know what knot is, actually.
Tell me there is a...
Ah, damn.
Okay, never mind.
So this is greetings.
Greetings, I think I know.
No, no, actually.
The person said, go away.
Oh, okay, so that doesn't mean greetings.
This is just a line.
Let's think about this.
Um, so greetings.
Do I have greetings in some other language?
No.
Greetings?
Okay.
That means this one is correct.
This needs to be open.
There.
This is knot, huh?
What else is on this?
These two.
So this one needs to be up here.
Yeah.
Let's see what we get.
Knot!
Okay.
Wait.
Plural.
Alright.
Fear.
Open.
Oh, that could also mean unlock regarding the key.
Greetings.
Okay, we're getting somewhere here.
Why are these two lit and the last one is not?
Why is this one not filled?
Is it saying that the devotees are considered humans?
So are the bards, but these guys are not really considered humans?
Why it be like that?
Let's check out this terminal.
Ooh, yeah, we need some kind of special mold for that one.
Power?
No, I don't know what that means.
I think it means power.
Every time I get close to it, I hear this buzzing.
As if there's a generator behind there.
I mean, something's got to be generating these video games, right?
That is so weird what I'm seeing here.
This could also be power.
Coming in.
Or some sort of uplink.
Okay, let's go back now.
I want to see if these people have something new to say.
Or not new to say.
Maybe I had gleaned more information from it, given my new knowledge.
Right, this is where I'm...
Oh, I think I know what to put in here now.
Key.
Open.
Open, open, open.
There.
And door.
Which one is door?
That one.
Alrighty then.
Very good.
Which makes so much sense as well.
The key opens the door.
Right?
Oh my goodness.
Is that the number one ranked player on the ladder?
Highest MMR?
Greetings.
You're the one I was waiting for.
Oh yeah?
You want me to play your game?
Look at the way he's looking at me.
Ascend.
Door.
Oh, wait a sec.
Oh, that's so smart.
This means plural.
There's...
Oh, that's cool.
That's a really neat way to do it.
Wow.
Single?
Plural.
Right?
What is this?
Snap your fingers.
Either that or the Italian...
No, you know when you hold up your hand?
Go, go.
Maybe this means go up.
Go.
Up.
Hahaha.
Yeah.
And what do we have here?
This has to mean...
You.
Pointing at this guy.
You and...
Us.
Me.
Not me.
And the last one, obviously these two, but...
Follow me, go with me.
Oh, is that what it is?
It's like beckoning.
Alrighty.
Climb.
Ah, as in not me.
Doors.
Come.
Oh, nice.
Notice how the style of the drawings are also different.
Between each level, that's a nice detail.
You know, this is more rigid.
Whereas the drawings for the devotees was all flowy and, you know, very curvy.
Really cool.
Gotcha.
So here...
Ooh, this has to mean...
Oh, that's a tough one.
We have to combine these things now.
We have to think.
It's teaching us something.
What is this made of?
Actually, what is this made of?
This is made of one line.
Which is that one, not.
And a small line.
Do I have a small line somewhere?
Not really.
Not yet, at least.
What does this consist of?
This consists of us.
Me?
Plural.
You see that?
This is us.
It consists of this one and that one together.
Okay, this one is...
What is that?
This consists of a line which is not.
Let's see here.
Oh, it's very similar to this actually.
Look at that.
Oh, okay, not that similar.
Never mind.
Just a bit.
Where is this symbol up there?
I can't seem to find that.
In any of the others.
Okay, never mind that then.
What about this guy?
Or this guy?
What does that consist of?
It consists of...
That one for sure.
Dead.
And then something that goes across like that one perhaps.
Fear death.
That one could definitely be combined with this.
But then we're still missing a little line that way.
A little line that way could be...
Which one could that be?
This one.
No, there's a line down here.
That doesn't make sense.
It could be...
Not that one either.
Nope.
No.
Not that one either, but it's close.
Oh, this is a really interesting way of combining things.
Definitely this one.
But then we need a little bit in the top and a little bit down here and some there.
In fact, having this together with that wouldn't make sense.
Because this one already contains this, so to speak, you know?
So we need to combine fear with something else that contains a little bit of the top left.
A little bit of top right.
And then a line across there.
Top left, top right, and line across.
What could that be?
This one?
Wait.
Line across?
No, it has the line here.
That doesn't make sense.
Not that one.
Oh, this is a tough one.
I can't see it.
Not that one either.
Shit.
This one?
No.
Then again, if this was rotated, mirrored, it would work, but...
Then we have to mirror, seek, and what would that be?
I don't know.
Keys?
I don't think they go that deep.
Okay, let's wait with this a bit.
This is awesome.
Oh, there's more!
Okay, here we go.
Stop.
This is saying, what the fuck?
No.
Jesus.
Revived.
Not alive?
Not?
No, this is just death.
Dead.
Stop.
Not go.
And this is...
Not dead.
What does that mean?
Oh!
Whoops.
Okay, so obviously I didn't get it right, but why not?
He's obviously dead.
Am I missing something?
Not go.
Or maybe go not?
Maybe the order matters there?
I don't think it does.
They just combine the same way.
Not dead.
Does this mean go dead?
Become dead?
No.
Okay, what the...
Dead.
Not dead.
Not.
That's probably what it is.
Dead, not dead.
And this is just not.
What?
Okay.
Huh.
How is that not correct?
Go dead?
What the... That one makes no sense to me.
I mean, I have limited glyphs to work with here.
Not dead.
Unless I'm misunderstanding this?
Does this mean he is alive and then he became dead?
What?
So does this mean dead?
Maybe it's telling a story where this is he was dead, but then he started walking again.
So not dead, but then go.
No.
Not dead and go.
See, I would think dead.
No.
No dead.
Right?
Dead.
No.
No dead.
How is that not correct?
Do I just click next or something here?
Speak to me, man.
Why
have you been waiting for me?
Is it because you couldn't solve this puzzle on your own, so you needed me?
I can't solve it either, man.
I don't get it.
Oh, wait, wait.
Do we need to use everything?
I forgot what the last one was.
Did we have to use every single glyph?
Can we add two of the same?
No, we can't.
There's three goes.
Maybe go dead.
Go not.
And no.
Dead go not.
Go not dead.
Okay, that makes no sense.
What does that mean?
Die.
Stop.
Revive.
But wait a minute, that makes no sense.
Actually, maybe it does.
Hold on, I think I know what's going on here.
When you put go in front, you specify a verb.
Instead of saying death, when you say go death, that means to die.
When you say not, and you say go not, it means stop.
You know?
It actually does make sense when you look at it that way.
Ah.
Okay, okay, okay.
Countries.
Borders.
Nationalism.
Batminton.
My people need me.
Let's see here.
Me, plural.
Oh, community, I guess that one, remember?
Community.
What is that even?
Is that a magnifying glass?
Disregards science, acquire video games, which is pretty much what I've been doing.
In real life, I mean.
Plural communities, many communities.
Here we have plural me.
Ah wait, that doesn't look like it's connecting very smoothly, so maybe not.
Seek.
Oh, not seek.
You don't want to search.
You don't want to investigate.
Not seek.
My community.
These are my people.
Yes.
Alrighty.
Peoples.
My people.
Us slash we.
Disrega- Isn't that what I said?
I said disregard science, acquire bitches.
I mean, video games.
Heh.
I was joking, but...
I also said my people.
Incredible.
Alright, alright, next.
Okay, that was it.
I did it, man.
Come.
I want one of those seats.
That's hella cool.
I follow you.
Oh my god, look at that hologram.
My people made the tower.
Yeah.
Yes, you did.
Strangers came to the tower.
Uh-huh.
Oh, you're sad now.
People stopped talking.
Peoples feared peoples.
Yeah, they became isolated.
Hold on.
Go back.
We know this now.
Community.
Solitude.
It has to mean solitude.
Exile, okay.
You've completed the translation of the Anchorites language.
I don't know what Anchorite means, but okay.
Maybe that doesn't matter.
Yeah.
My people left in exile.
We are dying.
The tower is dying.
Why did you leave in exile?
Because of all the newcomers that didn't want to...
integrate into a society?
I created you.
You're the key.
Oh my god.
It's the shape of me.
Help us.
You made me to connect everyone.
Make
the people talk.
Open the doors.
End the exile.
Revive the tower.
Oh, you got it.
I got ramsticks.
Yes, we can open doors.
Oh my god.
This also explains how I woke up...
in the beginning of the game, seemingly out of nowhere.
What the hell, man?
Dude.
Look at me.
I fit in there.
It's a me-shaped hole.
Yeah, okay.
I will.
My goodness, man.
This way.
Now to remember where the doors are.
I don't remember.
This way.
There should be one on this floor.
I think I saw one.
Was it up here?
This is video game land, right?
Not quite yet.
Where was this?
I think it was down here.
So I just came up from these stairs.
Oh no, this was not a door.
This was a terminal, right?
But that's okay.
By the way, I needed to confirm something real fast.
What does this mean?
Exile, okay.
Why would they have that on the doors?
Maybe people used to live in those quarters, and now they're gone, so, you know...
Exile?
Abandoned?
Tower, right?
Okay, people.
I see.
Man, the whole story just clicked.
That was amazing.
Oh, it's showing me the doors!
Okay, let's start from the bottom.
So if this door is closer to this one, I assume it means it's, well, closer to this one.
In real space as well, not just in this computer space.
Now to remember where it is.
I think this is towards the graveyard, if I'm not mistaken.
Yes, so I don't think there's a special door up there.
Oh, wait, is it...
Is it homing?
Hot or cold?
Okay, it's still beeping.
Uh, let's see, what is this way?
Oh, it's not beeping anymore.
It's cold.
Here?
It's still beeping this...
A little faster?
Okay, okay.
Sweet.
Up here?
This way.
Oh, that's neat.
Oh, it's beeping fast.
Where's the door?
Here?
No, wrong way.
This way.
Boy, am I glad that this homing thing is active right now.
Otherwise, I would have taken forever to find this door again.
The beeping is out of control.
Open the door!
What's in here?
Oh, no way!
Look at that!
They designed everything.
The musical instruments, the coins...
Oh my God, dude.
Wait, is he controlling these people?
Mind control?
Why does it look like he's about to die?
Man dies of thirst.
It's a devotee.
Devotee...
Oh man, I don't know.
Preacher!
Right?
Preacher.
That's the preacher.
Wait a minute.
What was this?
I found the lens.
The lens found God.
I'm going to the cemetery.
I'm going up.
The preacher.
Oh God, I don't know.
Ooh.
What is he doing?
He's observing potions.
Crafting potions?
I don't understand.
The preacher...
Preacher creates...
potions?
But then we're missing one.
Maybe he seeks potions.
Does he love the potions?
Ah man, I...
I have no clue what that is supposed to...
represent.
Like, at all.
Exile.
What is going on?
I don't
get it.
A costume of a devotee.
What is he doing in there right now?
Am I supposed to find this spot?
Is this a live feed?
Ah man, preacher.
Preacher...
creates...
something potion?
Does
he talk to the potions?
What is he doing?
Preacher found God...
in the booze?
Preacher helps...
the plants.
No, what is... hmm.
I found the lens.
The lens found God.
I'm going to the cemetery.
I'm going up.
So where the hell is this guy anyway?
If he went up...
how come I haven't seen him?
Isn't that interesting?
Unless...
the preacher...
was this guy?
Is this guy the preacher?
Was he controlling him?
Could we say that?
The preacher...
is a plant.
He's an industry plant.
Oh, I don't know.
Let's try one of the others.
Maybe that will elucidate things.
I'll be back.
I have no clue.
I love the music in there though.
Okay, now I know where this is at least.
Oh no, it didn't beep anymore.
I'm going to...
have a tough time finding this again, I think.
Okay, so if we can get to here, it's just that way.
Remember that.
That should be easy enough.
Damn it, man.
So that way.
Okay, gotcha.
So we get here, we go that way.
All right.
That should be easy enough to find.
Let's try the next.
Take me to...
here.
The warrior domain.
Now to remember where this thing was.
Okay, yeah.
Going the right way.
Up here.
We can only go that way.
That's where I came from.
Is it really this far?
Okay, it's beeping fast.
Here maybe.
No.
That way.
I mean, it's just trial and error.
And it has to be here.
Why is it always the last thing I choose?
Damn it.
Really?
So where is it?
Huh?
Oh, I don't think I've ever been here.
Oh my God.
Slotted in.
My, look at all this.
Wait, is that the missing piece of the...
thing we saw earlier?
Weapons.
Oh man, look at that.
Did they create the languages for these guys as well or what?
Let's see this one.
The warriors are carrying the boat.
Reminds me of that coffin ritual from some, I don't know, country out there where the people just dance with the coffin on their back.
You know what I mean?
Not scientists, what am I saying?
The warriors arrived by boat.
Don't we also have something very specific regarding that?
We have like a drawing, right?
Oh wait, this is the wrong language.
Maybe it's not on here.
We could just be literal here.
Warriors carrying the vessel.
Okay, so we're going to need plural and warrior.
Where are you at?
Warriors come out to play.
There.
Warriors carry,
carry, possess vessel.
Okay, so that's very literal.
Oh,
what the...
What the actual freaking fuck is this?
Huh?
That's me.
And I'm glorious.
It's a me-shaped hole.
Make up your own joke about that, okay?
Oh my god.
Hello.
I am exile.
Come to me.
Come into exile.
Eh?
Wait,
I'm not sure I want to do that.
Do I want to do that?
Oh, I turned it off.
Okay.
Wait, I'm actually kind of confused here.
Come into exile.
Oh, is that what they call it when they play video games?
To go into exile?
Oh.
Greetings.
You entered my exile.
My people will revive the tower.
Ha ha ha.
Yo, we're establishing a connection.
Oh, that's interesting.
Look at the way this thing can be plugged into the seat.
Everyone is stuck playing video games.
We got to get them out.
Okay, so now we know we have to be very literal with those translations.
So maybe we go with the devotees love potions or something like that, right?
It could be as simple as that.
Now we go to the next.
It just feels a little arbitrary, you know?
The warriors are carrying the vessel.
Like, what a random thing to translate, right?
It doesn't have any significant meaning, I don't think.
Not at first glance, at least.
This way.
Over here.
Now we teleport.
Let's go to the parts.
It's part time.
Here.
Yeah, I think I know where it is.
Wait, it was in the Agora.
I do remember that.
There's got to be a different way to continue down here.
What about here?
Yeah.
Yes.
Here.
This way.
Towards the theater, remember?
There it is.
Yes.
Oh yeah, baby.
Let's get in there.
Let's go.
It also makes so much sense now.
All these doors are purple.
The same color as the architects, or what do they call themselves, the archetypes?
I forgot the name.
Does it say in here?
There's definitely something like archangel, or...
Look at all these things.
Artifacts from this civilization, or this culture.
Let's free this guy from his exile.
Okay, the bards are going to the theater.
Right?
But we have to reverse it, so be careful.
To the theater, the bards go.
So...
Theater...
To the theater...
Hold on.
Two...
Oh, wait, I fucked up.
Don't we have a two?
Glyph somewhere.
Path.
The path to theater...
No, no, actually, this is fine.
Because we have to go plural here.
I forgot if it came first or after, I think.
After.
So that would be...
Bard, plural, go.
Yes!
What the frick?
That is scary as hell.
Oh my god.
That's horrible.
Run!
No!
I got sapped!
Jesus!
How on earth are you going to do this?
That's horrible.
Oh, I think I may know how.
Exile?
Here?
Oh my god.
Wait, there's a...
Oh, look!
These have been released!
This guy is missing over here.
Are you afraid to die?
I'll help you.
The people of Exile do not die.
Quite the contrary, in fact.
They get to become heroes or villains, whatever they want in these virtual worlds.
You can be whoever you want.
I don't care about that.
I choose real life, but only in the video game.
In real life, I choose video games.
Boom.
Power off.
Look at him.
What are you now, huh?
You have been freed.
I'll help you.
I will end Exile.
I will speak to peoples.
Do it!
Who are you contacting?
The Bards.
Right.
Okay, okay.
Good shit.
Let's move on.
In fact, I may be comfortable enough to do the devotees now.
I think I know what we have to do.
Did I come from down here?
I actually don't remember now.
Yes.
Good shit.
Here.
Back to the devotees.
Go, go, go.
Dude, this is hype.
This way.
Up, up, up, up, up.
Ascend, climb.
This way.
Up here and then to the right.
Down that way.
And here we are.
This guy is just still vibing.
Completely unaware.
Oblivious to all the stuff happening around him.
Okay, here we go again.
So what are the devotees doing?
They are creating products.
They are...
They love potions.
Let's just say that.
So, devotees.
That would be one of these tall ones.
Devotee.
Let's say love potions.
No, okay.
So I guess we can say devotees create potions.
No?
They look at potions?
There is no way, right?
Let's see here.
Look.
Do I have look?
Or do I only have seek?
Oh, I do.
What?
Oh, wait, wait, wait, wait.
I'm an idiot.
Preacher.
The potions are plural here.
Love potions.
What?
Okay, preacher creates potions.
Okay, preacher looks at potions.
Look at the potions.
What?
He looks at potions?
What the hell kind of sentence is that?
All right, whatever.
Oh, God.
Ooh.
I think they're upping their security based on what I have been doing previously.
So they're going around like that, huh?
It's just... okay.
I'm scared.
I don't know what to...
Can I not just...
Uh...
Oh, shit.
Go...
Fucking hell there, quick.
Jesus Christ, man.
Run!
Oh.
Thank God.
Oh, you're angry now.
Don't stop me.
I help the people.
Your help is not needed, thank you.
I was sent here to disable you and that's what I'm doing.
No more exile.
The time for video games is over.
God, I hate saying that.
But it's true in this case.
Okay, here we go, buddy.
You help me.
I will help the tower.
I'll speak to the... yeah, speak to the people.
Ooh, yeah.
Preach it, brother.
Okay, okay, let's go.
What is the next?
Uh, it is alchemists.
And I know where that is, I think.
Actually, I don't know where that is, I forgot.
But we have the homing locator.
Or homing beacon.
I
can't believe the preacher was looking at potions.
That makes no fucking sense.
What?
That is the weirdest sentence.
Uh, okay.
So we did that, we did... oh, right, it's even indicated here.
That way.
So where the hell was this?
Here, I think.
Oh, so good.
Do it.
Open up that door.
The machine is going to be angry now, though.
He's going to dispatch all of his sentries.
Nice.
Uh, books?
A pile of books?
Huh?
Oh!
Two?
Oh, wait, we have to count.
One, two, three, four, five, six books.
Uh, so six is that one and...
Oh, but can I do that?
No, we have a six, of course.
What am I doing?
Six books.
Plural.
Where's books at?
There we go.
Not bad.
All the sentries dispatched?
Yeah, here we go.
Oh, but wait a minute, there's four sentries missing here.
And only three moving around.
Where's the last one?
God, they're so creepy.
Uh, not sure where to go here.
So what does this guy do?
He goes back and forth like that, or what?
Okay, so I have a window here to go up here.
I see.
That's a big window.
And then when I'm here...
I go straight for that door.
Yeah, that's the strategy.
Let's do it.
Oh, I just missed it.
Fuck, I was too late.
No.
Oh, that's too...
Oh, I had the window there.
Shit.
Wait for... Oh, look at how angry he is now.
He an angry boy.
Okay, now we wait for this guy to go back.
Go.
Ha ha ha.
Damn, son.
Go!
Fuck, fuck, fuck, fuck, fuck.
Oh, shit.
Oh, I hate that.
Is he not going to see...
Okay, he turns that way.
Okay, that's actually nice.
Hide here.
Oh, my goodness.
Go, go, go, go.
You're a stranger.
You're not my people.
I will stop you.
Oh, yeah?
How you gonna do that?
I'm gonna go over here and click this button.
What do you think of that?
Boop.
Stay mad.
Yeah, you people ain't shit.
Ah, but there's still one missing.
Where is he?
Am I gonna get a shock now?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You'll speak to the people, do that.
Tell them about everything that happened here.
And don't forget to mention what I did.
Okay?
My contribution is vast.
My name shall go down.
If I even have a name.
Probably not.
What is this creepy sound?
That was a creepy sound just now.
Okay, well, look at this.
It's completed.
Let's head up here.
And talk to the Overlord.
If I remember where that is.
Oh god, this way?
Uh, maybe.
Maybe up here.
I'm not sure what this is doing here.
What this is...
Actually, hold on.
This is the same sort of thing we saw when we deactivated the machines.
There was also this beep beep beep beep beep going up and down on each side.
Information being exchanged or whatever.
We go here now?
Okay, but wait.
I kind of want to talk to the dude again.
Oh, never mind.
Oh shit.
Oh, he sapped me.
I'm okay.
Hold on.
I'm not moving on yet.
I got to talk to the dude.
Tell him that I did the thing I did.
Oh.
Okay.
I guess there's no going back now.
Well, shit.
That was actually kind of scary.
Oh, wow.
Are we really going to the very top?
Look at the clouds down below.
But how's it raining up here then?
Maybe more clouds up above.
Go into the darkness.
The tunnel of shadow.
What the fuck?
Also, what's that?
Wait a sec.
Eh?
Oh, okay.
Then I appear from this side?
Okay, that's weird.
Something's going on here.
What the hell?
Activate it.
Oh.
The end?
Whoa, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
What?
New game plus?
Uh...
Say what?
I'm so confused right now.
Why did it not turn on?
Also, what was I turning on?
Wait, what?
Something looks off here.
I'm losing my mind.
Whoa!
Huh?
Come here.
Okay, yeah, things are fucked.
How do I come there?
Oh, thank you.
You guys about to say something looked off here?
What the hell?
This way.
Wait a minute.
Has everything been a simulation?
The glitching.
Am I in exile?
Am I also just playing video games?
Uh...
Nothing is real.
Child, converse with me.
Oh, look at these.
Are you kidding me?
Uh...
Wait a minute, what does this mean again?
Exile.
The warriors push back the impure.
Uh...
Impure.
No?
Uh, what is...
Hold on.
Oh, wait, wait, wait, what's this?
Oh yeah, it's saying warriors.
Hold back the impure, what was it again?
Protect the bards, maybe.
Warriors protect the bards.
Goddammit, where are the bards?
Chosen.
What?
Hold on.
I can also go this way.
What's that all about?
No, no, no, no, no, I want to solve this.
Let me see here.
Exile.
What the hell is happening here?
Okay, what I think is happening, I push the terminal on top of the tower.
And...
Uh, this machine is giving me my last, you know, trial, so to speak.
It's trying really hard to hold me back for the last time, but I have to push through.
What does this symbolize?
I
forgot what that meant.
Do we have a drawing here?
Chosen, impure.
Oh.
The warrior pushes back the impure.
Protects the chosen, carries the duty, maybe it's that one.
Carries the duty.
The duty was, let's see if I remember.
No, okay, I don't remember.
Are you kidding me?
Uh, well, I don't know.
Did I, maybe I typed it wrong.
Pushes.
Impure.
Huh.
Maybe, okay, so maybe that's not what it says.
Maybe I have to rethink this.
God damn it.
Warriors.
Okay, wait a minute.
I see a little bit of what's going on there.
Wait, is that Bart language?
What I'm seeing there?
There's three up like that.
Could be that one.
Hold on, let's try and move on a bit.
I'm not quite sure about this.
Let's see what's up here.
Oh my God, look at the eyes down there.
Weird doors and weird locations.
Yeah, this is all fucked.
Oh, here we go.
Okay.
Oh, everything is warped.
Hold on, I gotta see this.
Have we been fed a story?
That was incorrect.
The call.
The chosen ones, yeah, they are impressed by the chosen ones.
The warriors are building the fortress.
The impure ones making...
music.
Oh!
We changed history in a way.
Right?
It turned out the devotees were also making music.
That's what we communicated via the terminals.
So they're not actually pushing back the impure anymore.
Or the devotees.
Okay, so warriors...
I forgot what I just read.
Fuck, what did I just read?
Oh, I forgot.
Make music.
But why would it say this over... Okay, wait, wait, wait.
Back.
The impure ones make music, right?
Impure ones create...
music.
Okay, good, good.
Let's see.
You're happy about that?
Oh, okay.
We're glitching through the matrix here.
What's up, dude?
You're an idiot, am I?
Look at his face mask.
I can give him something.
Look at that, that's all messed up.
Glitch in the matrix.
Let me drink from the wine.
The piswasa.
Unhappiness.
Exile.
Hey, do you want this?
I need you to come operate this elevator for me.
Because I can't do it alone.
There you go.
Like a petulant child.
I don't like you.
You're a monster.
You're a monster, a monster.
Am I?
Hold on, I can go here?
No, wait, a child is coming out of there.
What's up, child?
I'm free.
Yes, you are.
That's what the other child said as well.
That puzzled me for so long.
That child said, we're free.
Go up.
Okay.
Elevate me, child.
Man, I've been dreaming of riding this elevator.
Oh, God, what's going on over there?
Ooh.
Yeah, that's messed up.
Let's see a show.
What's up, idiot?
You were searching for the saw.
You were looking for the music.
You tried the flames.
And then you tried the compass.
And then you resorted to violence.
And you found the door.
Oi, yo, wasi, yappa.
That actually kind of scared me.
You found the alchemists.
Okay.
What's that story about me?
I didn't resort to violence, though.
That means theater.
What?
Books?
What the...
Let's see what this actually meant.
Oh, this is all fucked up.
North he went, instrument he found.
West he went.
The saw he found.
The path the idiot bard sought.
And then something.
Then he found something else.
Yeah.
The idiot bard found the path.
Sure, I totally did.
If this says books, though, why...
I thought maybe this would change to a library when I went back up.
Go down.
Man, I'm loving this sort of paradoxical architecture here.
You know, Penrose stairs and Asherian stairwells or whatever they're called.
Not exactly that, but you know.
That ballpark.
Click on that.
Okay.
Um...
The path the idiot bard found.
Let's say that.
Idiot here?
Good.
Path...
The path...
The idiot...
Bard...
Found.
No?
Hmm.
Wait a sec.
What's this way?
Oh, I can't go that way.
Hmm, okay, okay.
This door is gone now.
There's something I'm missing here.
The thing that stood out to me was the weapon.
Right?
North...
Instrument...
Saw...
The path is...
Wait.
This is also in the wrong order, I think.
Weapon, the bard found.
Is that the one?
Because that one stood out to me a little bit.
The idiot bard would never resort to violence.
Uh, idiot bard.
Oh, wait, wait, wait.
We have to do it opposite, of course.
Maybe I was right.
The path...
No, no.
I did it right before.
I said...
Path...
Idiot bard found.
But let's just, um...
Try the weapon.
Weapon...
The idiot...
Bard...
Found.
A?
Huh.
The door is open in the back there.
Did I really fuck it up last time?
Maybe I wrote it wrong.
The
path...
God, where's the path?
Path...
The idiot...
Bard...
Found.
You gotta be kidding me.
I don't know.
We gotta watch that play again.
I have no clue.
This one is stumping me.
Up, up, up, up.
Let's watch this again.
Okay, so this is clearly what we're seeing in the preview.
The two trees and the door.
You went west and found the saw.
You went east...
And found the instrument.
You went south or north and found fire.
And you found the compass.
And you found the sword.
Ah, maybe it's, um...
Alchemists.
The bard found.
Being specific here.
Right?
That could be it.
He found the alchemists.
I mean, he found the path as well, but...
Mostly the alchemists.
And when I say he, I mean me, obviously.
It's me!
I'm the one!
Okay, let's see here.
Uh, so that would be scientist here.
If they even have that word.
Oh my god!
Wait, what?
Then I don't know.
Did I miss it?
Brother?
Could be one?
Let's try that.
Brother the idiot bard found.
Ah, ha ha, yeah!
We know that!
Oh shit!
We're here.
Full circle.
Except we haven't been to the alchemist place yet.
Oh no, no more games!
Exile at the very top.
Okay.
Every one of those cards has become an exile card.
That's been blocked off.
Let's check down here before we move to that obvious place we need to go to.
Oh yeah, we probably need to decipher something here before we do that.
Let's see the whole spiel unfold.
Notice by the way all the plants are dead now.
Let's see here.
God speaking to men.
Right.
And then men...
embracing God.
No, men became devotees, right?
Wasn't that how it was?
And then...
devotees seeking God.
On up high.
Wait, is this the same?
Have they changed something here?
I don't quite recall these murals.
Warriors closing the door.
That one I remember.
Right.
Closing the door.
But what happened in reality?
They ended up opening the door.
Right?
Let's see the display up here.
Sunrace.
Oh God, which one is that?
Let me double check down here.
Because it's pointing to one of the specific murals.
It's not these two.
It's not that one.
Wait, it's none of these.
Wait, do we have more?
No, this is... Oh, it's missing!
Oh, shit!
I don't remember what it was.
Oh, yeah, plants are dying or something.
Electrolytes.
It's what plants crave.
Gotta give it brondo.
The sun was killing plants or drying them out, whatever.
Oh, man, I actually don't remember that first mural at all.
Is it in here in my notes?
Don't think so.
Oh, what's this?
No, no, no, no.
Damn, I don't know.
Oh, man, uh...
Yeah, I... shit.
Wait, why is there... alchemist language here?
Oh!
The alchemists healed the plants.
So the plants didn't die, the plants got healed instead.
They gave them potions.
Or a... what was it?
Alchemists?
Healed?
Or not healed, what was the word?
Oh, God.
Okay, plant, that's good.
But do we have, like, a give?
Help, perhaps?
Help plants.
They helped the plants.
Okay, maybe it's just plants in plural this time, so instead of saying...
alchemists, we just say alchemists.
It was one guy, right?
Helped the plants.
No?
Uh, shit, I don't know.
This one is a real head scratcher.
I don't know, man.
In fact, what am I even looking at?
This doesn't look like plants at all.
I'm seeing... people on the left, and...
Hold on, are we doing warriors open the door?
Instead of closing it?
Oh my God, I don't know!
I don't recall the first mural!
Hold up.
Let's go even further back.
Let's try going all the way back here.
Yeah, what's down here?
What the frick?
Oh, you're kidding me, there's more clues down here!
That was a plural sign.
In the alchemist language.
Oh, there it is.
There it is, dude.
Yeah, that's what I was trying to say!
The alchemist helped the plants!
Okay, created formula, maybe?
So...
Formula was down there.
Do we have other pieces lying around, other than this one?
Why can't I interact with this?
That's plural, isn't it?
Let's see here, that one.
Yeah, that looks like plural to me.
Okay.
I guess we try to do that.
Why not?
Okay, that didn't do anything.
Why did I do that?
I don't know.
Yeah, alright.
Let's go back up.
Let's try combinations with formula now.
They created formula.
Formula one.
I was trying to click up there and see if he would run all the way up on his own, but he didn't.
Literally unplayable.
Okay, so alchemist created brondo.
That healed the plants.
So, we are going to say...
alchemists.
God, where were you?
Create.
Come on.
God, I swear to God.
Like, having to sift through all these every time is probably the worst part about this game.
They should really have added a search function, or something.
To the ones I've already discovered.
Then have them highlighted, you know?
Ah, worst create, dammit.
I'm going through everyone again.
Let's see.
It's not even here.
Make.
Thank you.
Formula.
Where is that?
There.
Okay.
Oh, hey!
Oh, he's angry.
Oh, my God.
Oh, shit.
Run!
Oh, God.
Quick.
Oh, my God.
This is all fucked up.
Don't look back.
Keep going.
Down, down, down, down, down, down.
What the hell?
Reality ain't real.
Uh-oh.
Okay, I'm coming, I'm coming.
Thank you, child.
There's skulls everywhere.
I was not expecting there to be a chase sequence in this game!
Where do I go?
Up, up, up, up, up.
This way.
Here.
Shit!
What's the way?
Left.
Down.
Where am I going?
Okay, okay, we gotta go north.
This way.
Up, up, up, up, up.
No, don't click the book, you idiot.
Right, right, right.
Go, go, go.
Go right, right.
Good.
Keep going.
I don't care, everything's upside down.
Water's coming.
Exiles.
Oh, they're all statues of monsters now.
Joe!
On the boat, on the boat.
Oh, we ran across the boat.
I thought we were getting on the boat.
Pull it.
Oh.
Nice.
Yeah, simulation, baby.
I'm still on top of the tower, aren't I?
Hug me, friend.
Wait, what?
Is that me?
Wait.
Have I been...
in exile this entire time?
Since the beginning of the game?
Or was I brought here by this guy?
At the very end.
When I was on top of the tower.
There's only two solutions.
Oh.
I was in there.
Greetings.
You stopped exile.
You revived my people.
I did.
Everyone...
is now free to take a break from gaming.
They're grateful.
You helped my people.
Exile is dead.
And...
exile truly is dead.
Which way?
Let's go in here.
Let's see if the dude is still here.
Are you in here?
Oh, I think he's gone.
I want to sit in here.
I want to place my body inside of there.
What's this?
Right, it's showing me all the doors.
That's okay, though.
We move on.
This way.
Dude, the game totally faked me out with that ending.
Or fake ending.
Look at him, they're having a post-gaming discussion.
What's down here?
And what about up there?
I want to see if anything's changed.
Okay, then I'm back here.
So if I go down this way now...
Aha!
The bottom part.
You came to help us.
You stopped exile.
I sure did.
Have I been down here?
Oh, let's see if we understand this now.
The tower.
The people.
We are the people of exile.
We welcome the peoples of the tower.
Oh...
I get it.
It all makes sense.
Well, no surprise, I guess.
Since we figured out the language.
Okay, let's head up to the door again.
So I was actually in exile the entire time, controlling another body of mine in this place?
But wouldn't that sort of suggest that this place is also a simulation?
Unless I went on top of the tower, I got captured by one of the sentries, brought down here, put into that room, marked exile.
And then stuff happened.
Look at this, this is off now.
Because of me.
Go.
Oh, look at this!
It's all happy.
I love happy.
The colors are good.
No more rain.
The clouds are gone.
Never mind, the clouds are still here, but they're beautiful.
Pretty clouds.
Run, little man!
Faster!
Come on!
Move those feet of yours.
Okay, I was half expecting a tunnel of light this time, but okay.
I'll take it.
Look at everyone's here!
What's up, guys?
Hey!
I mean, they're still sort of isolated a little bit.
They stay in their cliques, but okay.
Guys, start mingling!
Establishing connections, literally.
That's what that represents, of course.
Oh, it's God!
It's all kinds of things.
Oh, that's cool.
You can create all the languages.
It's the ultimate Rosetta Stone.
They're mingling!
Where's the Hochduvrat?
Where's the finger food?
Delicious snacks.
Where's the champagne?
This is great.
The child is finally conversing with me.
Oh, that's nice.
That is so good.
What a beautiful ending and what a fakeout.
I legitimately thought I had reached the ending and that I perhaps had done something wrong.
I thought, oh, did I miss a power source to turn off somewhere so that I actually got a bad ending or somehow?
But no!
I did it right!
Oh, that's so nice.
Is it going to zoom all the way out?
This was really fun.
Great puzzles.
I enjoyed the language stuff, even though I'm not very good at languages.
I got stuck on some of the puzzles, especially in the beginning of the game, but I had so much fun with it.
And...
I can't believe how everything's just sort of connected at the end.
Literally, right?
But also in the other sense.
I remember the first time I saw those zoom terminals, I was so confused.
By the TIE fighter and the dots moving around.
I thought it was just an aesthetic thing, you know?
Oh, it's going to look, you know, futuristic-y and sci-fi-ish.
But no, there was a meaning behind all of it.
Especially the way the three-dimensional polygon there that we made at the end can symbolize all the glyphs of all the languages when you project it onto a 2D surface.
It's almost like I'm a sphere that arrived in Flatland, you know, Edwin A.
Abbott?
Because if you come from above into Flatland, you can see all the rooms, a.k.a.
languages, and you can connect them all together.
You know?
I am God up on high!
It was me!
I looked down upon the land.
The Flatland, right?
And I saw all these civilizations isolated in their little squares.
And each civilization couldn't see the other civilization, a.k.a.
talk to them, because of the geometry of Flatland, right?
I came in from the top and I allowed everyone to establish connections.
That was great!
Thank you for playing.
Thank you for making it!
Great Game Run disc.
Holy shit.
Blew me away.
I hope my analogy there at the end made any sense.
I don't know, maybe it didn't.
In any case, thank you for watching and checking out this Let's Play.
This was great fun.
And thank you all for the recommendation.
This was truly a 10 out of 10 for me.
Holy shit.
So good.
I loved every part of it.
Except that one little bit, you know, about not being able to search the glyphs other than that.
A perfect game from start to end.
Really enjoyed it.
As you probably could tell by my excitement throughout.
Alright guys, I'll see you in the next video.
Whatever that may be.
Have a great one, alright?
Take care.
Also, if you're still here, I don't know if you are, but if you are and you haven't subscribed or liked or left a comment yet, it would be amazing if you did.
Thank you.
Bye bye.